<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN" "../../dtd/docbook-4.1/docbookx.dtd"> 

<book>   
  <bookinfo>     
    <title>Xerlin 1.1 User Guide</title>
    <authorgroup>       
      <author>  
	    <firstname>Kelly</firstname>
	    <othername>A.</othername>  
	    <surname>Campbell</surname>
	    <affiliation>    <jobtitle>Software Engineer</jobtitle>    
	        <orgname>ChannelPoint, Inc.</orgname>  
	    </affiliation>       
      </author>
      <author>
	    <firstname>Justin</firstname>
        <surname>Lipton</surname>
        <affiliation>  <jobtitle>Product Manager</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SpeedLegal</orgname>
        </affiliation>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>     
      <revhistory>       
        <revision>
	    <revnumber>1.1</revnumber> 
	    <date>July 7, 2002</date>
	    <revremark>Draft for Xerlin 1.2 release</revremark>
      </revision>     
	  <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>September 10, 2000</date>
        <revremark>Initial draft for 1.0 release</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <copyright>       
	<holder>
This User Guide is based on a document originally prepared for the Merlot 
XML editor, the original open source project on which Xerlin is based.  The
original Merlot User Guide was written by Kelly Campbell, and is copyright
(c) 2000 Channelpoint, Inc.  The Xerlin User Guide is being made available
as an integral part of the Xerlin open source project, and any contributions
to the User Guide are accepted on the basis that they will be made freely
available to users of Xerlin, subject to the Xerlin open source license.
	</holder>
    </copyright>  
  </bookinfo>  
  
  <chapter id="chapt-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>     
    <para>Xerlin (pronounced zer-lin)
      is an application for creating XML files. It runs on Java 2
      virtual machines (JDK1.2.2 or JDK1.3). Xerlin simplifies how
      you interact with an XML file by hiding the raw text form of
      XML. It gives a user interface for adding, removing, and
      rearranging XML elements. It also gives a nice interface for
      editing the attributes of elements. Xerlin has been
      developed for end users who may not be familiar with XML,
      but it also provides a useful interface for people who know
      XML really well.</para>     

    <para>An example of what the
      Xerlin interface looks like is given in <xref linkend="fig-intro-merlot-interface"/>       
      <figure id="fig-intro-merlot-interface">  
	<title>Xerlin Interface</title>  
	<mediaobject>    
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-intro-merlot-interface.gif" format="GIF"/>           
          </imageobject>           
          <caption><para>A screenshot of the Xerlin XML interface</para>
          </caption>         
        </mediaobject>       
      </figure>
    </para>     
    <section id="div-intro-about-xml">
      <title>About XML</title>       
      <para>A full explanation
	of XML is beyond the scope of this document, however we
	will cover some of the basic XML concepts you will need
	to know in order to use Xerlin prodcutively.
	<acronym>XML</acronym> stands for eXtensible Markup
	Language. It is similar to <acronym>HTML</acronym>,
	HyperText Markup Language, except users can create their
	own tags to fit their application needs.</para>

      <section id="div-intro-elements">  
	<title>Elements, Attributes, and Content</title>  
	<para>The basic
	  construct in XML is called an
	  <emphasis>element</emphasis>. For people familiar
	  with HTML, you might know this as a "tag".
	  For example, HTML has an &lt;img&gt; element for
	  putting graphics on a web page. Elements have a
	  name, zero or more attributes, and possibly some
	  content. In the raw text form of an XML document,
	  elements start with a beginning tag of the element
	  name enclosed within angle brackets (&lt; &gt;). XML
	  elements must have a closing tag of angle brackets
	  enclosing a slash and the element name. If the
	  element has no content, this slash can be inserted
	  at the end of the element's starting tag
	  immediately preceeding the trailing angle bracket.
	  An example of an element is given in 
	  <xref linkend="example-intro-xml-elements-raw"/>
	</para>  
	<example id="example-intro-xml-elements-raw">
	  <programlisting format="linespecific">
   &lt;elementname attribute="value"&gt;content&lt;/elementname&gt;
	  </programlisting>
	</example>  
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Attributes</emphasis> are named values
	  associated with an element. An example of an
	  attribute is shown above in <xref linkend="example-intro-xml-elements-raw"/> The
	  <emphasis>content</emphasis> of element can be other
	  elements, text, or both. When an element has both
	  text and other elements, it is known as "mixed
	  content". Text content is also known as
	  <emphasis>character data</emphasis>,
	  <acronym>PCDATA</acronym>, or
	  <acronym>CDATA</acronym>.  </para>  
	<para>Xerlin
	  supports most of these constructs of XML except
	  CDATA. CDATA starts with <literal moreinfo="none">&lt;![CDATA[</literal> and ends with
	  <literal>]]&gt;</literal>. CDATA items are not
	  currently supported as of Xerlin 1.2, but should be
	  supported in a future release.</para>
      </section>       
      <section id="div-intro-dtd"> 
	<title>DTDs and Schemas</title>  
	<para>XML uses something called
	  a Document Type Definition (<acronym>DTD</acronym>)
	  to determine what elements are valid for an XML
	  file, and what they can contain. A newer technology
	  called XML Schema has been introduced to replace
	  DTD's. However since this is such a new
	  technology (it hasn't been finalized as of this
	  writing), and the parser technologies Xerlin has
	  been built on top of don't support it, Xerlin
	  doesn't support Schemas in version 1.0.</para>
	<para>To be able to add elements and create a valid
	  XML document, Xerlin requires a DTD in order to
	  work. There are many different DTDs available for
	  different applications, and there are books and
	  tutorials available on creating DTDs. Without a DTD,
	  Xerlin cannot present it's menu of what
	  elements can be added into the document. You can
	  view and edit documents which don't have a DTD,
	  but you will not be able to add anything new to
	  them.</para>  
	<para>The DTD is specified in an XML
	  document in a special element called the
	  <emphasis>DOCTYPE</emphasis>. This document type
	  declaration includes the name of the root element,
	  an optional PUBLIC identifier, and a manditory
	  SYSTEM identifier. Xerlin handles the DOCTYPE
	  declaration and the identifiers behind the scenes
	  for you. A future version may give you more access
	  to edit these items directly.</para>
      </section>     
    </section>    
  </chapter>    
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>   
    <!-- <highlights> -->
    <para>Xerlin is very simple to install. This chapter will
      tell you  
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">    
	<listitem>      
	  <simpara>what you need to download</simpara>
	</listitem>    
	<listitem>
	  <simpara>how to unpack the distribution</simpara>
	</listitem>    
	<listitem>
	  <simpara>how to check that your installation works</simpara> 
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <!--  </highlights> --> 
    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>   
      <para>Xerlin requires a computer system with the following:  
	<itemizedlist spacing="compact">    
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>Java 2 Standard Edition (see below)</simpara>    
	  </listitem> 
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>Relatively fast processor (300Mhz or higher for Intel architecture
                        chips)</simpara>   
	  </listitem>  
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>At least 32MB of RAM, 64MB or more recommended</simpara> 
	  </listitem> 
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>  
      <para>Xerlin requires a Java Virtual Machine
	(JVM) which implements Sun's Java 2 Standard
	Edition. Recommended versions are JDK or JRE version
	1.2.2 and later. Xerlin has been tested to work with
	Sun's JDK 1.2.2 and 1.3 on Windows, Linux x86, and
	Solaris (x86 and sparc) platforms. It has also been
	tested with IBM's JDK 1.3 on Linux. Other platforms
	with a working JVM of these versions should work fine,
	but haven't been fully tested. Sun's Java 2 SE
	is available from <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">http://java.sun.com/j2se/</ulink>.
	You need either the Runtime Environment, or the SDK.
      </para>       
	<para>Note: As of this writing, there is no
	  Java 2 Platform for the classic MacOS (7, 8, or 9).
	  However, MacOS X has a Java 2 Virtual Machine which
	  we have not yet had a chance to test Xerlin
	  with.</para>    
    </section>  
    <section>
      <title>Download</title>   
      <para>The latest release of
	Xerlin is always available at <ulink url="http://www.xerlin.org/">http://www.xerlin.org/</ulink>.
	Click on the Download link in the navigation bar.
	Download the current release for your system. There is a
	Zip file for Windows users, and a Gzipped Tar file for
	UNIX users. You just need the binary release to run
	Xerlin. The source distribution is available separately
	for those developers who want to use it.</para>
    </section>   
    <section>    
      <title>Unpack</title>
      <para>You can unpack the distribution anywhere you want
	on your system. Simply expand the zip or tar file and
	move the Xerlin-1.2 directory it creates where you want
	it.</para>   
    </section>  
    <section>   
      <title>Run Xerlin</title>    
      <para>To run Xerlin, simply double-click the 
	<filename moreinfo="none">Xerlin.bat</filename> application if
	you're on Windows, or run the
	<filename>Xerlin.sh</filename> shell script on UNIX (you
	may need to make it executable first). You can also
	start Xerlin from a command prompt with 
	<command moreinfo="none">java -jar Xerlin-1.2.jar</command>.
	The Xerlin splash screen should appear, and begin
	loading the application. If any major errors occur
	during startup, some kind of error message may appear in
	the command prompt terminal window.        </para>
      <para>  If this starts up and gives you a blank window
	with menus at the top, you have successfully installed
	Xerlin. The next chapter will get you started in using
	Xerlin to create and edit XML files.       </para>
    </section> 
  </chapter>   
  <chapter>     
    <title>Working With XML Documents</title>  
    <!-- <highlights> -->
    <para>In this chapter we will cover some of the basics of
      creating XML documents with Xerlin including  
       <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
	<listitem>  
	  <simpara>creating a new XML document from a DTD</simpara>  
	</listitem> 
	<listitem>
	  <simpara>adding, editing, and deleting elements</simpara> 
	</listitem>   
      </itemizedlist>
    </para> 
    <!--  </highlights> -->  
    <para>The Xerlin user
      interface is shown in <xref linkend="fig-interface-callouts"/> It has the typical
      application menus such as <guimenu>File</guimenu> and
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, and a shortcut Toolbar. Multiple
      document windows can be open at one time, and managed with
      the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> menu and the actions available in
      the titlebar of each window. </para>      

    <figure id="fig-interface-callouts">  
      <title>User Interface</title>       
      <mediaobject> 
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/fig-interface-callouts.gif" format="GIF"/>  
	</imageobject>  
      </mediaobject>
    </figure> 
    <para> At the left is the Element Tree which shows the
      structure of the xml document. If you've worked with
      the DOM interface for XML, this tree is just a graphical
      representation of the DOM document. To the right is the
      attribute edit panel where you set the attributes for an
      element and where plugins can add specialized element
      editors. </para>  

   <section>  
      <title>Creating a new document</title>
      <para>Xerlin can create new
	documents, or work with existing ones. In both cases,
	you must have a valid DTD describing the possible
	structure of your document as dicussed in 
	<xref linkend="div-intro-dtd"/> To start a new document,
	select <guimenuitem>New File</guimenuitem> from the
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu, or click the New File button
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject>      
	    <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar-newfile.gif"/>
      </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> on the toolbar.
      </para> 
      
      <para>When you create a new document,
	Xerlin must first setup the DOCTYPE for the XML file.
	First, you must select a DTD file. Xerlin brings up the
	DTD Chooser panel shown in <xref
					 linkend="fig-dtd-chooser"/> for you to select a DTD from
	a plugin or from your local filesystem.  </para>
      <figure id="fig-dtd-chooser">     
	<title>DTD Chooser Panel</title> 
	<mediaobject>  
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-dtd-chooser.gif" format="GIF"/>    
	  </imageobject> 
	  <caption>
	    <para>Select a DTD, or Browse your filesystem
	      for one, then click OK</para>   
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>   
      </figure>  
      <para>The DTD's shown
	initially are from DTD plugins installed in the Xerlin
	plugins directory (see <xref linkend="chapt-plugins"/>).
	The labels given are the DTD's PUBLIC identifier
	given by the plugin config. When you've opened
	documents or selected other DTD's on your
	filesystem, those new DTD's will also show up on
	your DTD Chooser until you quit Xerlin. If a DTD
	doesn't have a PUBLIC id, the SYSTEM id is shown on
	the DTD Chooser instead. Select the DTD you want to use,
	and click the OK button.</para>  

      <para>If there are
	errors in the DTD file, an error message will be given
	such as in <xref linkend="fig-dtd-error"/> You will need
	to correct these errors in the DTD before you can edit a
	document using that DTD.    
	<figure id="fig-dtd-error">
	  <title>Error in a DTD</title>     
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/fig-dtd-error.gif" format="GIF"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>  
      </figure> 
      </para>  
      
      <para>If
	you're using a DTD from your filesystem Xerlin will
	ask for a Public id. If you don't want to set a
	public id for the DTD, you can just click the
	<guibutton>None</guibutton> button. Next Xerlin will ask
	for the root element as in <xref linkend="fig-root-element-chooser"/> You can select one
	from the list, or type one if you know which root
	element you want. Once you've created the document,
	you cannot change the DOCTYPE, including the root
	element, from within Xerlin. Note that DTD plugins can
	setup the DOCTYPE without involving the end user.
      </para>  
      <figure id="fig-root-element-chooser">
	<title>Root Element Chooser</title>     
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-root-element-chooser.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>  
      </figure>  
      
      <para>Once you have a new
	document (<xref format="GIF" linkend="fig-new-file"/>)
	you are ready to start adding new elements to it.
	<figure id="fig-new-file">  
	  <title>New Example Document</title>    
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/fig-new-file.gif" format="GIF"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject> 
      </figure> 
      </para>      
    </section>
    
    <section> 
      <title>Adding Nodes</title> 
      <para>To add new
	elements to your document, right-click on the item you
	want to add something to, and go to the
	<guimenu>Add</guimenu> menu as shown in 
	<xref linkend="fig-add-node"/>. Xerlin displays just the
	elements that are valid to add at the point specified by
	the element you right-clicked on. There are also menus
	for adding elements Before or After the given element.
	These menus are all built from the DTD at runtime, so
	you can only create documents which are valid according
	to the DTD.</para>  

      <figure id="fig-add-node">
	<title>Add Menu</title> 
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-add-node.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject> 
      </figure>  
      
      <para>When you add an element
	into another, it places it at the end of the parent
	element. Use the Add-&gt;Before and Add-&gt;After if you
	need to be more precise about where a new element should
	be placed.</para>  

      <para>You can also add comments and
	processing instructions from the Add-&gt;Special menu.
	These show up as "#comment" and
	"?pi?" in the Element Tree.</para>
    </section>    
    
    <section>
      <title>Editing Attributes</title> 
      <para>When you add a new
	item to the Element Tree, the element's attribute
	editor is added to the right-hand pane allowing you to
	set attributes, and text for the new node. 
	<xref linkend="fig-attribute-edit"/> shows the attribute
	editor for a new &lt;p&gt; using the Xerlin Example DTD.
	
	<figure id="fig-attribute-edit">    
	  <title>Editing
	    Attributes</title>      
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/fig-attribute-edit.gif" format="GIF"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject> 
      </figure>  
      </para> 
    </section>  

    <section id="div-moving-removing">    
      <title>Moving and Removing Elements</title>  
      <para>There are two ways to move
	elements and restructure your document. On platforms
	which support Drag &amp; Drop, you can drag an element
	from the tree and drop it into a place where the element
	is valid according to the DTD. You can drop it within
	the same document or on another document of the same
	type. Lines and rectangles are drawn on the tree as
	you're dragging over it to show where the element
	would be dropped if you release the mouse. You can also
	drag items into the library as dicussed in 
	<xref linkend="chapt-library"/> If the drop location does not
	allow the item being dragged to be inserted at that
	point, an error message will appear for a few seconds in
	the status bar at the bottom of the document window.
      </para>    

      <para>The second and probably more
	reliable method for moving elements is to use Copy or
	Cut, and Paste. Use the copy and paste menu items
	available when you right-click on an element. These
	actions don't work from the menus for elements in
	the tree view with Xerlin 1.2. You can paste items into,
	after, or before another node. This works the same as
	the Add, Add-&gt;Before, and Add-&gt;After actions. Only
	valid pastes according to the DTD will be allowed as
	shown in <xref linkend="fig-paste-node"/> </para>
      <figure id="fig-paste-node">  
	<title>Pasting Nodes</title>  
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-paste-node.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject> 
      </figure> 

      <para>To remove
	elements, simply right-click on what you want to
	removed, and choose <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>.
	This removes the highlighted element and its
	sub-elements. If you accidentally delete something you
	didn't want to, Xerlin supports up to 10 levels of
	Undo. Undo also works for Cut, Paste, and Adding of
	elements.  </para>   
    </section>     
   </chapter>


  <chapter id="chapt-library">    
    <title>Using the Library</title>   
    <para>Xerlin has a feature which allows you
      to reuse elements between documents, or create templates of
      structures you use often. This is called the Library. You
      can drag any item from the Element Tree of a document into
      the library creating a new reusable element.  </para>   
    <section>
      <title>Creating a New Library</title>      
      <para>To use a
	Library, you first need to create a new one, or open an
	existing one. To create a new one, simply choose the
	<guimenuitem>New Library</guimenuitem> item on the
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu. Xerlin will ask for a name
	for the library. This is just a symbolic name you can
	use to keep track of different libraries. This name is
	used at the title of the library window. Next you will
	be given a Save File dialog. Choose a filename and
	location for the library file. Libraries are saved
	automatically when you close it, or when you quit
	Xerlin, so the file location must be determined before
	creating the library.</para>    
      <para>When you first
	have a new library, the window is empty. You must add
	sections to it before you can add any elements to the
	library. These sections provide a way to organize many
	items into categories. To add a new section, right-click
	in the library window, and choose <guimenuitem>New
	  Section</guimenuitem> as shown in <xref linkend="fig-library-new-section"/>
      </para> 
      <figure id="fig-library-new-section">
	<title>New Section in a Library</title>  
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-library-new-section.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject> 
      </figure>  

      <para>After you have a
	section, you can add items by drag &amp; drop as
	discussed in <xref linkend="div-moving-removing"/> or
	copy and paste into the section you want to put
	something in.   </para>  
    </section>  
    <section>
      <title>Using Elements from a Library</title>
      <para>Once you have a library with your templates and
	other elements you want to reuse, you can use the items
	by copy &amp; paste, or drag &amp; drop. The same
	DTD-based rules apply to elements coming from the
	library as to elements from other documents. If there is
	more than one element in a library item, then only the
	first element is checked for validity with the
	destination. Also, Xerlin 1.2 does not enforce that the
	document an element came from and the document it's
	being pasted into have the same DTD or doctype.</para>
      <para>The Library is automatically saved when you quit,
	or when you close the library window. If you
	specifically want to make sure your changes to the
	library are saved, you need to close the library
	window.</para>    
    </section>   
  </chapter>  
  <chapter id="chapt-plugins">    
    <title>Plugins</title>  
    <para>Xerlin supports two different kinds of plugins, DTD plugins and
      Action plugins. These plugins can be developed for
      application-specific uses of Xerlin as discussed in the
      <ulink url="http://www.xerlin.org/docs/plugins/plugin-dev-guide.html">Plugin
	Development Guide</ulink>.  
    </para>  
    <para>Plugins
      are usually a jar file which you simply install in the
      <filename>plugins</filename> directory of Xerlin. Xerlin 1.2
      includes two example plugins, the example plugin, and the
      XSLT plugin. The Example plugin has a very simple DTD and
      one custom editor which allows you to pick a color from a
      color chooser. The XSLT plugin translates an xml document
      using a &lt;?xml-stylesheet href="url"?&gt;
      processing instruction.  
    </para>   
    <para>For more information on plugins, and to download thirdparty plugins for Xerlin, see the Xerlin web site.</para>

  <section>
      <title>DTD Plugins</title>      
      <para>DTD Plugins provide a
	way to add DTDs to Xerlin's DTD Chooser, and
	special editing actions for specific DTDs. DTD plugins
	show up on the Help-&gt;About Plugins menu, but not on
	the <guimenu>Plugins</guimenu> menu itself. When you
	start a new document or edit an existing document with a
	PUBLIC identifier which is the same as one specified by
	a DTD plugin, the DTD and custom editors associated with
	that plugin are used. DTD plugins can also provide the
	SYSTEM identifer and the root element to use for that
	DTD.</para>   
      <para>The Xerlin Example plugin has a
	custom editor which appears where there is a color
	attribute on elements for that DTD as shown in 
	<xref linkend="fig-plugin-example-color"/> This attribute
	would normally have a textbox where you can enter the
	hex value for a color, but with the example plugin, you
	get a button which allows you to use a graphical color
	chooser. The color you choose is converted to the hex
	notation and saved in the xml file in that format.
      </para> 
      <figure id="fig-plugin-example-color">
	<title>Custom Color Attribute Editor</title>    
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/fig-plugin-example-color.jpg" format="JPG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>  
      </figure>   
    </section>  
    
    <section>
      <title>Action Plugins</title>
      <para>Action plugins
	perform an action on the foreground document. For
	example, running an XSLT transformation on the document. Action plugins are listed in the <guimenu>Plugins</guimenu> menu.
      </para>   
    </section> 
  </chapter>   

  <colophon>
    <para>This publication was produced using the
      <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/xml/index.html">DocBook XML
	DTD</ulink> with Xemacs and the PSGML package, and with
      Xerlin 1.2. The HTML version is rendered via Norm
      Walsh's <ulink url="http://www.nwalsh.com/docbook/xsl/index.html">DocBook
	XSLT stylesheets</ulink> using
      <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/xerces-j/index.html">Xerces-J</ulink>
      and <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/xalan/index.html">Xalan-J</ulink>.
      The PDF version is rendered with Norm Walsh's XSLT
      stylesheets and <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/fop/index.html">FOP</ulink>.
      Graphics were produced using <ulink url="http://www.gimp.org/">The GIMP</ulink> on Linux.
        </para>  
    <para>The HTML document is best viewed with Explorer 5.0 or later, or Mozilla/Netscape 6 because of the CSS stylesheet used to format the XSLT generated document.</para>
  </colophon> 

</book>
